<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Richard Baxter's account of his present thoughts concerning the controversies about the perseverance of the saints. Occasioned by the gross misreports of some passages in his book, called, The right method for peace of conscience, &amp;c; which are left out in the last impression to avoid offence, and this here substituted, for the fuller explication of the same points.</title>
            <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76135</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866804</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119090</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942696</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E939_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207773</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866804</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866804e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76135)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E939[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Richard Baxter's account of his present thoughts concerning the controversies about the perseverance of the saints. Occasioned by the gross misreports of some passages in his book, called, The right method for peace of conscience, &amp;c; which are left out in the last impression to avoid offence, and this here substituted, for the fuller explication of the same points.</title>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Underhill at the Anchor and Bible in Pauls Church-yard, and F. Tyton at the three Daggers in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LVII. [1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the saints perseverance.</note>
                  <note>Annotation in Thomason copy: "Aprill 26", Roman numeral "I" added to imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Right method for a settled peace of conscience and spiritual comfort.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterianism --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Perseverance (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119090:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>RICHARD BAXTER</hi>'s ACCOUNT OF His present Thoughts CONCERNING the Controversies about THE Perseverance of the SAINTS.</p>
            <p>Occasioned by the gross misreports of some passages in his Book, called, <hi>The Right Method for Peace of Conscience,</hi> &amp;c; which are left out in the last Impression to avoid offence, and this here substituted, for the fuller ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the same Points.</p>
            <bibl>LUTHERUS, referente Hopffnero Saxon. <hi>Evangel.</hi> p. 110.</bibl>
            <q>Nihil pestilentius in Ecclesia doceri potest, quam si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, quae Necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria non sunt, Necessaria fiant: Hâc enim tyrannide conscientiae illaqueantur, &amp; libertas fidei extinguitur; mendacium pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, Idolum pro Deo, abominatio pro sanctitate, colitur.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Ʋnderhill</hi> at the Anchor and Bible in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>F. Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> at the three Daggers in Fleetstreet M. D C. LVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119090:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119090:2"/>
            <head>OF THE SAINTS PERSEVERANCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving let fall some passages concerning Perseverance, in a Book entitled <hi>The Right Method for Peace of Conscience</hi> in 32. Directions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> agreeable to the state and experience of my own soul: no sooner were they published, but many suspicious Brethren gave out, that I had wrote against the certain Perseverance of the Saints. How little reason they had for their report, I manifested in the next Edition by an Apology. But the case is come to that at last, even with pious Brethren, that they know my Belief much better than I know my own: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to tell them my Judgment, is in vain. But because I cannot think that all are so sagacious or censorious, and because I think it meetest to the utmost of my power to avoid offence, and to leave out controversie as much as may be in such practicall Writings, I have, in the last Edition of the Book, left out all those passages that occasioned mens mistake, and withall the additional Apology, (as being then needless:) But lest any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119090:3"/> think that hereby I betray any truth of God for the pleasing of men▪ I have thought meet, in these few Pages, to declare what my Judgment is in that point, more largely and more seasonably than in the aforesaid Writing. And it is not my design to stand upon the maintenance of the Opinion which I own, or the confutation of the contrary: but only, to give to my mistaken, offended, censorious Brethren a true account of my mind.</p>
            <p>There are many Opinions concerning this Point among the Professors of the Christian faith; which I think meet to set down, that I may the better declare my own thoughts of the whole. And I shall begin at the utmost extreme on one side, and proceed on to that on the other side, taking the middle O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions in the way.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The first Opinion which I shall mention, is that of the Papists, who do not only hold the Doctrine of actual Apostacy of Saints, but also that every mortal sinne, as they call them, doth excuss the Spirit of grace, and put a sinner not only under an actual guilt, but also into an unjustified estate, and so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a state of death and damnation: so that a state of grace (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them) is frequently lost with many, and frequently recovered. If any would see this Point open'd and debated judiciously, let them read <hi>Rob. Baronius</hi> his small <hi>Tractate de Peccato Mortali &amp; Veniali.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The second Opinion is, that the truly Regenerate and justified (indefinitely) may and do (some of them) fall totally and finally from a state of grace or justification, into a state of death and condemnation; and perish everlasting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. This Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion excepteth not the Elect themselves considered Antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but only considered consequently: because it is a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to be Elect and yet not to persevere: For the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of it hold that God doth Elect men only upon foresight of faith and perseverance, and not to perseverance and faith it self; For they deny any Antecedent absolute election to the first differencing grace: and deny any such grace it self, as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119090:3"/> by an insuperable operation shall infallibly convert. This O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion was too common among both Greek and Latine Fathers, that wrote before the daies of <hi>Augustine,</hi> as appeareth both by express passages in many of their Writings; and by their Doctrine of free-will, and predestination upon foresight of the good use thereof, and other Points that inferre it: which <hi>Scultetus</hi> and many other of the reformed Divines do <hi>inter naevos Patrum</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite. And though they saw that this would not consist with a certainty of salvation, yet they chose rather to deny that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, than to assert the Perseverance of all the Regenerate; and to say, as <hi>Origen,</hi> and after him <hi>Eusebius Preparat. Evangel. lib. 6. pag.</hi> 289. 290. [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,—i. e. <hi>Immo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnarent ista secum ut idem &amp; probus evaderet, &amp; certo probum se futurum esse praenosset.</hi>] And <hi>Augustine</hi> himself (as afterward) hath the like or more <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Serm. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>de septuages.</hi> saith, <hi>Qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test dicere, Ego de electis sum? Ego de praedestinatis sum ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam aeternam? Ego de numero sum filiorum Dei: Quis haec inquam dicere potest? reclamante nimirum scripturâ: Nescit homo si amore dignus sit, an odio. Certitudinem igitur non habemus; sed spei fiducia consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur nos,</hi> &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p>Yea, when they saw that this was lyable to be assaulted with the absurd consequence of inferring a change in God, some did not stick upon it: as <hi>Tertull. contr. Marcion. lib 2. cap. 23, 24. Per tot si vero etiam circa personas levem vultis intelligi, quum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probat aliquando probatos, aut improvidum, quum probat quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doque reprobandos, quasi judicia sua aut damnet praeterita, aut ignoret futura: at qui nihil tam bono &amp; judici convenit quam pro presentibus meritis &amp; rejicere, &amp; adlègere,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Opinion possesseth the farre greatest part of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world at this day, but in <hi>Europe</hi> the chief friends of it are those that are called Arminians and Lutherans, and abundance of the Jesuites and their followers, who also take in the first Opinion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Opinion is, That no certainty of Perseverance doth arise from Election, nor can be concluded from our meer ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification and adoption and sanctification: for they think that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119090:4"/> there is no such thing as Antecedent Election of persons indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidually, to faith and salvation: and they think that many of the truly justified and Regenerate, do fall away and perish for ever. But yet they say, that there is a certain height of holiness, which is attainable in this life, which whosoever attaineth shall never fall away. If you ask what is that height or state: I answer, They are obscure teachers who hold this, that shun the clear disclosure of their minds, and therefore I cannot fully answer you: only thus much I can say, that I have met with those of them that express themselves these several waies. Some of them say, that there is a state of sinless perfection attainable in this life: and that those that are thus perfect shall not fall away. Some of them make new descriptions of the Covenants, and say, that those that are under the first Covenant may fall away, but not those that are under the second: I confess I do not fully understand their describing and differencing the Covenants. And some affirm, that there is in this life, a state of confirmation, consistent with Peccability and venial sinnes, which whosoever attaineth shall never fall away. They think that the Angels themselves were first made righteous without confirming grace: and then confirmed as a reward for their adhereing to God, when the rest fell. And so, that <hi>Adam</hi> should have been confirmed as a reward, if he had conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the first temptation and adhered unto God. And so, that Christ doth first set men in an unconfirmed state of Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and life, and will confirm them and put them beyond the perill of falling away, upon certain termes or conditions, (whose punctum or discernable state, they do not tell us.) The persons holding this third Opinion are the Paracelsians (under whom I comprehend the Weigelians and the rest of the Enthusiasts) and many newly risen in <hi>England.</hi> And it seems by <hi>Hom.</hi> 26. that holy <hi>Macarius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">This seems also <hi>Origens</hi> Opinion, as may be seen in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Fol. (<hi>edit Ascens.) 193. Col. 2. 194. c. 2.</hi>
               </note> inclined that way. And it is the Opinion of some later Papists: Of which more under the fifth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth Opinion is, That God hath not only decreed that all that will believe and persevere shall be saved; but also that such and such persons by Name, shall by his differencing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119090:4"/> free, effectuall grace, be infallibly brought to faith and perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and therefore none of the Elect shall ever totally and finally fall away or perish: But yet that some are effectually called, Regenerated, Justified and Sanctified, besides the Elect: and these will all fall away and perish.] This was the opinion of <hi>Augustine,</hi> who rose up against <hi>Pelagius</hi> and his followers in defence of differencing free grace, and first plainly and fully vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated that Grace against the exalters of Nature and free will: whom the contrary minded do now unjustly accuse of running too farre, even into a contrary extreme in the heat of his dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations against <hi>Pelagius.</hi> Because some are so immodest as to deny this to be <hi>Augustines</hi> Doctrine, I shall add this much: 1. I askt the reverend Bishop <hi>Ʋsher</hi> in the hearing of D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Kendall,</hi> Whether this were not plainly the judgment of <hi>Austin?</hi> who answered, that without doubt it was. And he was as likely to know as any man that I am capable of consulting with. 2. If any be in doubt, these passages following, among many other, may end his doubts.</p>
            <p>August. <hi>de bono persever.</hi> c. 8, &amp; 9. [<hi>Ex duobus autem piis, cur huic donetur perseverantia us{que} in finem, illi autem non donetur; inscrutabiliora sunt judicia Dei. Illud tamen fidelibus debet esse certissimum; hunc esse ex praedestinatis, illum non esse.</hi> Nam si fuissent ex nobis, <hi>ait unus ex praedestinatorum, qui de pectore do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini bibebat hoc secretum,</hi> mansissent uti{que} nobiscum. <hi>Quid est quaeso,</hi> non erant ex nobis, <hi>&amp;c. nonne utri{que} vocati fuerant &amp; vocantem secuti? utri{que} ex impiis justificati</hi> &amp;c? <hi>Quaenam est tandem ista discretio? Patent libri Dei: non avertamus aspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. Clamat Scriptura divina: adhibeamus auditum: Non erant ex nobis, quia non erant</hi> secundum propositum vocati: <hi>Non erant in Christo electi ante constitutionem mundi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nam si hoc essent, ex illis essent, &amp; cum illis sine dubitatione man sissent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem</hi> Lib. <hi>de corrept. &amp; gratiâ.</hi> cap. 8, &amp; 9. [<hi>De his enim dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serimus, qui perseverantiam bonitatis non habent; sed ex bono in malum deficiente bona voluntate moriuntur. Respondeant si possunt, cur illes Deus cum fideliter &amp; piè viverent, non tunc de vitae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus periculis rapuit ne malitia mutaret intellectum corum▪ &amp; ne fictio deciperet animas corum? Ʋtrum hoc in potestate non habuit? An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum mala futura nescivit? Nempe nihil horum nisi perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sissimè at{que} insanissimè dicitur cur ergo non fecit?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quia, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrutabilia
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119090:5"/> judicia ejus,</hi> &amp;c.—9. <hi>Nec vos moveat quod fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis suis quibusdam Deus non dat istam perseverantiam. Absit enim ut ita esset, si de illis praedestinatis essent, &amp; secundum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positum vocatis, qui verè sunt filii promissionis. Nam isti cum piè vivant, dicuntur filii Dei: sed quoniam victuri sunt impie, &amp; in eadem impietate morituri, non illos dicit filios Dei praescientia Dei.—Non quia justitiam simulaverunt, sed quia in ea non permanserunt: Nam si fuissent ex nobis, veram, non fictam justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam tenuissent uti{que} nobiscum,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>vid. ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem de corrept. &amp; grat.</hi> cap. 8. <hi>Hic si a me quaeratur cur eis Deus perseverantiam non dederit, qui eam qua Christianè vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent dilectionem dedit? Me ignorare respondeo: Non enim arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantèr, sed agnoscens modulum meum audio dicentem Apostolum, O homo tu quis es,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ibid</hi> cap. 12. <hi>Quamvis ergo de omnibus regeneratis &amp; pie vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventibus loqueretur Apostolus dicens, Tu quis es qui, judicas ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum alienum? suo domino stat aut cadit. Continuo tamen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spexit ad praedestinatos, &amp; ait:</hi> stabit autem.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem de dono persever.</hi> cap. 22. avoiding the harsher expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions that might offend, he teacheth them to substitute such as these: [<hi>Si qui autem obediunt, sed in regnum ejus &amp; gloriam praedestinati non sunt, temporales sunt, nec us{que} in finem in eadem obedientia perman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bunt.</hi>] The same he hath before and there frequently.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem de correp. &amp; grat.</hi> cap. 8. <hi>Mirandum est quidem, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum{que} mirandum, quod filiis suis Deus quibusdam, quos regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit in Christo, quibus fidem, spem, dilectionem dedit, non dat perseverantiam</hi> &amp;c.] Ib. cap. 9. [<hi>Propter hoc Apostolus, cum dixisset,</hi> Scimus quoniam diligentibus Deum omnia cooperantur in bonum: <hi>sciens, nonnullos diligere Deum, &amp; in eo bono us{que} in finem non permanere, mox addidit;</hi> his qui secundum propositum vocati sunt: <hi>hi enim in eo quod diligunt Deum, permanent us{que} in finem,</hi> &amp;c.—Ibid. cap. 6. <hi>Si autem jam regeneratus &amp; justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus in malam vitam sua voluntate rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bitur, certè is non potest dicere, non accepi; quia acceptam gratiam Dei suo in malum libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro amisit arbitrio</hi>]</p>
            <p>Ibid. cap. 12. <hi>Dicit Johannes Apostolus,</hi> Est peccatum ad mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, non pro illo dico, ut roget quis: <hi>de quo peccato quoniam non expressum est, possunt multa &amp; diversa sentiri: Ego autem dico
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119090:5"/> id esse peccatum, fidem quae perdilectionem operatur deserer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us{que} ad mortem.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abundance of such passages makes</hi> Aust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns <hi>mind, as plain as his Pen could express it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor did he stick at the utter overthrowing of all certainty of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation hereby (except conditional.) As appeareth de</hi> cor. <hi>&amp;</hi> grat. c. 13. pag. 539. (Saris.) <hi>Quis enim ex multitudine fidelium quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu in hac mortalitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vivitur, in numero praedestinatorum se esse praesumat? quia id occultari opus est in hoc loco; ubi sic cavendae est elatio, ut etiam per Satanae Angelum ne extolleretur tantus col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lophizaretur Apostolus—Nam propter hujus utilitatem secreti, ne forte quis extollatur, sed omnes etiam qui benè currunt, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, dum occultum est qui perveniant. Propter hujus ergo utilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem secreti credendum est quosdam de filiis perditionis, non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto dono perseverandi us{que} in finem, in fide quae per dilectionem operatur incipe vivere, ac aliquandiu, fidelitèr ac juste vivere, &amp; postea cadere, ne{que} de hac vita priusquam hoc eis contingat, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri. Quorum si nemini contigisset, tamdiu haberent homines istum saluberrimum timorem, quo vitium elationis opprimitur, donec ad Christi gratiam, qua piè vivitur, pervenirent; deinceps jam securi, nunquam se ab illo esse casuros. Quae presumptio in isto tentationum loco non expedit, ubi tanta est infirmitas, ut super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam possit generare securitas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Idem</hi> Epist. 101. <hi>ad</hi> Vitalem. [<hi>Ʋtile est quippe omnibus, vel pene omnibus propter humilitatem saluberrimam, ut quales futuri sint scire non possint.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et in</hi> Lib. 11. <hi>de Civitate Dei</hi> cap. 12. pag. 670. [<hi>Quis enim primos illos homines in Paradiso negare audeat beatos fuisse ante peccatum? quamvis d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sua beatitudine quam diuturna, vel utrum aeterna esset incertos? esset autem aeterna nisi peccassent. Cum bodiè non impudenter beatos vocemu;, quos videmus juste ac piè cum spe futurae immortalitatis hanc vitam ducere sine crimine vastante conscientiam, facile impetrantes peccatis hujus infirmitatis divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam misericordiam? Qui licet de suae perseverantiae praemio certi sint, de ipsa tamen perseverantia sua reperiantur incerti? Quis enim hominum se in actione profectu{que} justitiae perseveraturum us{que} in finem se sciat, nisi aliquae revelatione ab illo fiat certus qui de hac re justo latenti{que} judicio, non omnes instruit sed neminem fallit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119090:6"/>
            <p>Of the same mind with <hi>Austin,</hi> were <hi>Prosper, Fulg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntius</hi> and the rest of the highest defenders of free grace, that the Church for many ages did enjoy: as appeareth in <hi>Prosperi Respons. ad Gall. Sentent 2. &amp; super Sent. 7. &amp; 12. &amp; ad object. Vincent. object. 12. &amp; passim. Ita &amp; Fulgentius.</hi> I forbear to recite the words, as having been too long on that already.</p>
            <p>The same doctrine of <hi>Augustine, Prosper,</hi> &amp;c. do the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans maintain against the Jesuits; as may be seen in <hi>Alvarez Disput.</hi> 107. and commonly in others: as also in <hi>Jansenius, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pererius</hi> and some few of the Jesuites joyn in the main with the Dominicans. <hi>Vid.</hi> Perer. <hi>Disp. 28. in 8. Rom &amp; Disp. 6, 7, 8.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>de Grat Christi, lib. 9. c. 7. p. 392, 393. &amp; sequent. &amp; lib. 3. c. 20. p.</hi> 163, 164. who is more exact than most other Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, especially in the point of predestination, and the nature of Grace.] The same opinion also some of the Reformed Protestant Divines maintain: as <hi>Musculus Loc. com. de Remission.</hi> § 6. <hi>pag. (mihi)</hi> 620, 621, 622. and D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Overall</hi> in the short addition to <hi>Davenants</hi> Dissertations (wrongfully fathered on <hi>Davenant,</hi> as BP <hi>Ʋsher</hi> told me.)</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth Opinion is; That God Electeth all that he will save, to Faith and perseverance, and that some are confirmed in this life in a state of Justification, and so are past the danger of Apostasie: so that either Election or confirming Grace, will necessarily inferre the certainty of perseverance: for neither the Elect nor the confirmed shall finally fall away. And they sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that many are elect which are not confirmed; and none confirmed but those that are elect. But yet they adde, that there are many truly regenerate, justified, sanctified, adopted, and live in love and obedience to God, who are yet neither elected nor confirmed: and that all these will certainly fall away.</p>
            <p>This Opinion is the same with that of <hi>Augustine</hi> last mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that it addeth, the non-apostatizing of the confirmed, to the non-apostatizing of the Elect. And <hi>Vossius</hi> supposeth that <hi>Augustine</hi> himself was of this mind, and joyned this point with the former. Of which I am not able to determine: For though I am as sure as words can make me, that <hi>Austin, Prosper</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentius,</hi> are of the last mentioned opinion; yet I cannot say so of this, because the footsteps of it in their writings are so few and dark, that to me they are uncertain.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119090:6"/>
            <p>Most of the Domincians go this way, and some Jesuites part of it, but then they scarcewell agree about the nature of this confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace. <hi>Viguerius</hi> (a Collector out of <hi>Thomas</hi>) and others say, that it is nothing but the gift of Perseverance it self. Others admit a reall distinction between the grace of confirmation and perseverance, who yet agree not in the nature or effects. For some think that Habitual infused Grace, and speciall assisting Grace, are enough to perseverance, but not to confirmation: some say a third sort is necessary to perseverance also, and that a Reprobate may have the two former. Some Papists think, that confirming Grace doth take away Free-will in obedience, and cause such a determination of the will to good, that they do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily obey, and so they are not freely but necessarily saved: These Papists hold this, it seems, because their definition of free▪ will is so far inconsistent with the Dominicans, that when they yeeld that Confirmation doth so effectually determin the will, they must needs say that it takes away its liberty, as they think Heaven it self doth, <hi>viz.</hi> by perfecting the will, and raising it to a higher pitch than liberty. But another part of the Papists (of whom it is that <hi>Alvarez</hi> speaks, <hi>lib. 10. Disput. 104. pag.</hi> 419. §. 1.) do hold, that the Grace of Confirmation and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, are distinguished only accidentally, by a greater or less intension of the same Helps, but not Really. The fuller expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their opinion and their reasons, you may find in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Disputation.</p>
            <p>But the Opinion which <hi>Ferrariensis, Alvarez,</hi> and others of that Classis do maintain, as the common opinion of the <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> is, that the Gift of Confirmation and Perseverance is not the same: that all the Elect persevere, but all are not here Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: And for the point of <hi>Impeccability,</hi> they agree with the Jesuites, that the <hi>Confirmati</hi> are <hi>Impeccabiles</hi> as to mortal sin; but not as to venial (to which they annumerate, the remnants of ignorance, inconsiderateness, the <hi>fomes peccati,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Vid. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varez Disput.</hi> 104. §. 4.) This Impeccability as to Mortal sin, is the perfection, or fulfilling of all Gods Commandements, which the Papists mean and say, we may attain. But then some of them say, that this Immpeccability is only to be ascribed to intrinsick Grace: others with <hi>Durandus</hi> (in 3. <hi>d. 3. q.</hi> 4) do ascribe it only to extrinsick removall of the occasions of sinne: some think
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119090:7"/> that it is partly from intrinsick Grace, and partly from extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick; that is, <hi>ex perfectione Gratiae habitualis &amp; virtutum, &amp; ex custodia, protectione &amp; directione Dei</hi> (as <hi>Alvarez.</hi>) Of these, the Dominicans ascribe it to a Physical Determining Grace (which Physical determination the most of them make necessary to every act of every creature; but <hi>Jansenius</hi> denieth that, and makes it specially necessary to saving good) and the Jesuites as is said, do most of them ascribe to a special sort of moral help leaving the will free: and others to a Necessitating determination. It is ordinarily judged (as <hi>Alvarez</hi> out of <hi>Thom.</hi> maintaineth) that this Impeccability is not simple, as not being <hi>ab intrinseco totaliter,</hi> but only <hi>secundum quid,</hi> as being <hi>partim ab extrinseco; quod contingit quando alicui datur aliquod munus gratiae quo inclinatur in bonum, ita ut ab illo non possit de facili deflecti; non tamen per hoc ita retrahitur a malo, ut omnino peccare non possit, nisi divinâ providentia protegatur &amp; custodiatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And its very observable wherein <hi>Alvarez</hi> placeth this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Perfection, <hi>ibid</hi> §. 4, <hi>viz.</hi> in a certain participation of <hi>Charitas Patriae,</hi> which is distinct <hi>secundum modum a Charitate violaris non Confirmante:</hi> His words are [<hi>Resp. non consistere in majori intensione ejusdem gratiae Habitualis. Etenim gratia non Confirmans, aliquando est magis intensa, quam gratia in bono Confirmans, quod ex eo patet: nam multi sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in via non Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmati in gratia qui habent gratiam &amp; charitatem magis inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sam, quam aliqui existentes in patria:</hi> (Believe this that can:) <hi>Dicendum est ergo quod haec perfectio attenditur secundum quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam participationem gratiae &amp; Charitatis Patriae, quae secundum modum est alterius rationis a gratia vel charitate non confirmante ut ait S.</hi> Thom 22. <hi>q. 24, art. 7. ad</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>As I account it more gross, according to the first opinion to say that every sinne which they call mortal destroyeth Justification, than to say only, that it is lost by some; and grosser to say, that All may fall away, than that All, save the Confirmed may fall away (which is the second opinion:) and that yet it is less culpable to say, that all the Elect shall perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, though not all the Justified (which is the fourth:) so I take this last recited to be less culpable than the fourth; because it alloweth a double ground of certain perseverance, that is,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119090:7"/> both Election and Confirmation, when the former alloweth but one.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The sixth Opinion is, That an Adult state of saving grace or Justification is never lost, but a state of Infant Justification may, because it is but a change of his Relation upon the condition of the Parents being a Believer.] Yet some of them deny not, but Elect Infants may some of them moreover have some secret seed of grace which is never lost.) Of this mind were the British Divines in the Synode of <hi>Dort;</hi> and <hi>Davenant</hi> and <hi>Ward</hi> have particularly wrote for it: and many more at home and abroad are of the same mind: And it should seem, so was the Synode of <hi>Dort</hi> it self, by those words <hi>Artic. 1. Can</hi> 17. pag. 244. <hi>Quandoquidem de volunta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Dei ex verbo ipsius nobis est judicandum, quod testatur liberos fidelium esse sanctos, non quidem natura, sed beneficio faederis gratuiti, in quo illi cum parentibus comprehenduntur, pij parentes de Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one &amp; salute suorum liberorum quos Deus in infantia ex haec vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta evocat, dubitare non debent.</hi>] Yet they that are of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion think it more fit to call this a cessation of their former Title to salvation, than a falling from grace as in their explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be seen.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The seventh Opinion is, That no one that is truly Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and Sanctified, doth ever totally fall away or lose the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of grace; but yet it is possible for them to fall away and lose it, though it shall never come to pass.] For it is not the Impossibility but the non-futurity that God decreeth. Of this Opinion are many of the Reformed Divines, called Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinists.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The eighth Opinion is, That for a Justified person In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant or Aged to lose that estate, is not only a thing that never shall come to pass, but that it is impossible for them to lose it: This is the Judgmenr also of very many Reformed Divines.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119090:8"/>9. The ninth Opinion is, that because it is impossible to fall away from grace, therefore it is unlawfull for any Believer to fear it, or, to perswade other Belivers to fear it; or to pray against it, or to think that any sin can endanger it; And though a Beliver did fall into Adultery and murder with <hi>David,</hi> or into Incest and Drunkenness with <hi>Lot,</hi> he ought not to fear the loss of his Justification, nor to be humbled with such considerations, nor to rise from the sin with such a Motive. This is the Judgment of the Antinomians commonly maintained in their Writings.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Another Opinion is, that, Though some degrees of saving grace may be lost, which by increase were supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added to the first grace which we received; yet no degree of the first habitual grace can be after lost by any sinne.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Another Opinion is, That though the Acts of grace may be sinfully omitted, and so grace may act weaklier than it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet the internal root or stock, whether you call it a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit or a power, or a new nature is never diminished, or lost in any degree, either which was at first infused, or is afterward infused by way of Augmentation.</p>
            <p>The two last Opinions are only dropt in by some few of the Reformed Divines, who are over-bold in their determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: The last is by most dis-owned; and the former by few of ours medled with in their Writings; but usually past over in silence.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Another Opinion about Perseverance is, That no sinne of a Believer, small or great, doth so much as contract on the person a guilt of death or any punishment; that is, an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to punishment: and that in Gods account we are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sinners, nor deserve damnation: for God seeth no sin in his people: the guilt falls all on Christ; and the punishment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119090:8"/> is all born by him alone; and no such thing as true punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment suffered by any Believer: And therefore that they may not confess the guilt of any sinne to be on themselves, nor pray for the pardon of it, but only when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y mean by [par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don] the feeling of pardon, or assurance or knowledg of it, or some new effect of it, in renewed mercies. This also is the known Opinion of the Antinomians, and the most extreme on this hand that is worthy our present Observation.</p>
            <p>Having thus shewed you the differing Opinions among Christians about Perseverance, I shall nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lay down so much of my own Judgment as I think needfull for the present pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, in certain <hi>Propositions,</hi> before I speak of the offence which do occasion it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. It is a gross Error to think that every sin which they call <hi>mortal</hi> or we call <hi>gross,</hi> doth excuss all Charity, or put a man out of a state of Justification. There are indeed sins that may be called <hi>mortal,</hi> eminently, which will prove a man out of the state of Grace, though they cannot be said to put him out of it, because he was never in it. I mean the sinne unto death, or the dominion of sinne, or any one sinne so aggravated as will prove that dominion, and so is inconsistant with saving grace. But it is not every act of a gross sinne that makes or proves a man to be unjustified. <hi>David</hi> was an adopted Sonne, an Heir of life, a Member of Christ, even a living Member, as soon as he had committed those heinous sinnes: though he contracted such a guilt, as anon we shall describe, yet his former guilt returned not on him (as many Schoolmen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves maintain) nor was he cut off from Christ, nor his state and Relation to him overthrown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object. Adam</hi> by one act did lose his habitual state of grace, and Relation to God, becoming unholy and unjustified: therefore so may we.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. I deny the Antecedent: For it was not by one Act, but by many that <hi>Adam</hi> so farre fell: 2. And I deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence: First, Because <hi>Adams</hi> sinne was such, as no regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man doth commit (for ought ever I have yet heard proved.) Secondly, At least, the difference of the Laws that he and we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119090:9"/> were under, would make this difference. For according to the Law that <hi>Adam</hi> was under, one sinne, yea any one sinne, did make him lyable to death, and consequently to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken by the grace or Spirit of God, and to be under the curse: But it is not so with a Believer according to the gentler Law of grace: The cause therefore of the difference is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally extrinsick in God and Christ and the Covenant of Grace: Whether there were any Internal, in the nature of the grace that <hi>Adam</hi> had, and that we have, I shall not now enquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. The Opinion of those Ancients, and of the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, Arminians and Lutherans, who deny an absolute perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Election of men to faith and Perseverance, and so maintain indefinitely a total and final falling from a state of justification, without excepting such Elect themselves, is an Eerror of dangerous consequence, against the grace and fidelity of God, if not against his wisdom and his power, and against the peace of the Saints: and therefore is to be carefully avoided and resisted, by those that would not wound their faith: as <hi>Augustine,</hi> and his followers, and since them the Dominicans and Reformed Divines have voluminously evinced.</p>
            <p>Yet note, that the Jesuites themselves may confess that the Elect shall none of them finally fall away, but shall all Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. But that is, because they hold that Election is upon the foresight of perseverance, and so that these Propositions are inconsistent as to their truth [This man is Elected] and [This man shall not Persevere:] But they do not make Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or differencing grace, the Cause of Faith and Perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. The third Opinion hath three Parts: Of which, I take one to be true, and the other two to be false. That which is true is, That the confirmed in grace, shall certainly Persevere. The Parts that I take to be false, are, First, That some of the truly justified, and sanctified are not Elect to salvation (which is common to them with <hi>Augustine.</hi>) Secondly, That
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119090:9"/> Perseverance is no fruit of Election, but only of mans good use of his grace, and of Gods remunerative Justice and Mercy: For they think that there is no Election of Individuals, but upon supposition of foreseen faith and repentance: so that this Opinion differeth not from the second, save only in that it addeth a state of confirmation, which none shall lose: and so maketh some in this life to be certainly past the danger of falling away: Of which more under the fifth Opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 4. The fourth Opinion, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Austin,</hi> with <hi>Prosper, Fulgentius</hi> and the rest of his followers that resisted the Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and of the Dominicans, and <hi>Musculus,</hi> &amp;c. who maintain personal absolute Election, and free grace, against the conceit of mans merits, and the certain Perseverance of all the Elect; and yet maintain that many of the <hi>Praesciti</hi> or non▪ elect are truly sanctified, and justified, and fall away from it and perish, doth seem to me to be unsound, and contrary to many Texts of holy Scripture, and therefore not to be received.</p>
            <p>To produce that Evidence against it, which is so common in mens hands in many Volumes written to this purpose, would here be worse than needless. And methinks <hi>Austins</hi> Exposition is a forcing of the Text. He expoundeth 1 <hi>Joh 2. 19. They were not of us, ie.</hi> of us the Elect. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 30. he expoundeth by prefixing to each linke the foregoing words, <hi>viz.</hi> the called according to his purpose: <hi>q. d.</hi> [whom he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>viz.</hi> according to his purpose, them he justified; and whom he justified▪ that is, those whom he so called and justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, them he glorified; <hi>q. d.</hi> those before mentioned whom he justified he glorified; or those whom he predestinated, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and justified (conjuncttly) them he glorified.] As if the Text did not comprehend all the Justified, nor speak of the Justified as such, but did only extoll Gods Love to the Elect, and consequently speak of them as Elect, and so of the Elect only, connexing every former Proposition in the chain with the later as necessary to make up its sense: as if the meaning were no more but this: [so great is the everlasting Love of God to his chosen, that he fore-knew them, and predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119090:10"/> them to be conformed to his Son; and having predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated them all, he effectually calleth them, and having cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them he justifieth them, and having justified them he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth them:] and so he would not have all others exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from calling and justifying, but only from predestination and glory. But I see not a sufficient warrant in the Text for such a limiting Exposition: It seems rather to me that [whom he called] is as much as [all whom he called] and [whom he justified] as much as [all whom he justified] And to me it seems unlikely, that ever such a love of God can change, by which he embraceth any man as a Sonne; For if Sonnes, than Heires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That love which made us Sons▪ and taketh complacency in us as Sons, will surely continneus in a state of Son-ship, and give us the Inheritance. How else can the little Flock be raised from their fears, because of the good pleasure of the Father to give them the Kingdom! For, alas, nothing more certain than that we should lose our grace, and so lose the Kingdom, if the Father had no other good pleasure towards us, but only to give us the Kingdom if we Persevere, and not also to give us perseverance that we may have the Kingdom. I know that <hi>Augustine</hi> distinguisheth of Sonnes; and some he saith may be called Sonnes because they are Regenerate, and justified, and in such a state as they should have been saved if they had died in; who yet are not Sonnes by predestination, but God fore-seeing their falling off, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth them not the Inheritance. But where he can find this distinction of Sonnes in Scripture, I know not: though another dictinction of Sonnes I confess may be found.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 5. Though I presume to dissent in this point from <hi>Augustine</hi> and the common Judgment of the Teachers of that and many former and later Ages; yet do I find my self obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Reverence of such contradicting Authority, and forced also by the consciousness of my ignorance, to suspect my own understanding, and to dissent with modesty, both honouring the contrary-minded, and being willing to receive any further evidence, and to know the truth if it be on their side. And so I must needs say, that I see not neer such clear evidence against this Opinion, as I do against the former, much less as I do for the Fundamental Articles of the Faith:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119090:10"/> and therefore I am not arrived at that certainty in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Perseverance of all the Justified, as I am for the Doctrine of the Perseverance of all the Elect; much less as I am about the death and resurrection of Christ, the Life Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting, and such other verities.</p>
            <p>I know that there is very great variety of evidence of the several Truths revealed in the Scriptures, one Text being more or less plain than another. Though we know that all that God saith, is equally true, yet we have not an equall evidence of every Truth, that it is indeed the Word of God. And therefore our reception of these several Points must needs be as unequall as the evidence is, upon which we do receive them. I dare not say that I have attained a <hi>certainty</hi> in understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Point and all the Texts of Scripture that concern it, better than <hi>Augustine,</hi> and the common Judgment of the Church for so many Ages: And therefore I dare not say that I have attained to a <hi>certainty,</hi> that all the justified shall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severe. I dare and I do venture my soul and everlasting hopes upon the truth of the Fundamentals; so that I dare, I must say; [If these be not true, I will forfeit my hopes; I expect no salvation.] But I dare not▪ I do not venture my salvation upon this Opinion; nor dare I say, [Let me have no salvation if any of the Justified fall from their Justification.] And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if I were put to it in arguing to deny either this or an evidenter truth, I would sooner reduce this to the more evident, than the more evident to this.</p>
            <p>And that it is not so evident as many others, or as that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon agreement in it by the godly can be expected, is apparent enough. 1. From the difficulties that occurre, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the dissenters reasonings may easily acquaint us with. 2. And from their answers to our Arguments. 3. And from the number and quality of the Dissenters. First, Sure that can be no very easie point which all or almost all the Church, for so many Ages erred in. Secondly, And which not only the most of the Christians of the world, but also so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations of Protestants themselves do err in to this day. Thirdly, And which the choicest men for Learning and diligence, and those that were the Leaders in defending the grace of God, as <hi>Austin</hi> and abundance of Protestant Divines, could never
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119090:11"/> attain the understanding of, but resisted them as errors. Fourthly, Yea when they were and are as holy as we; and so as like to have Divine Illumination. All this being in the case, it seemeth to be high self-conceited arrogancy, for such a one as I to prosess such a point to be so evident and easie, and to imagine that all the most holy and judicious Writers for so many Ages, and so many at this day, are so farre below me in the understanding of the Scriptures, and that even in points which they had so much occasion to search into, and so many and great advantages to understand. I do not, I dare not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 6. Hence it is most apparent, that this difference about the Perseverance of all the Justified, is not of so great moment, as to encourage or warrant us to withdraw our affection or communion from those that differ from us herein; as if they were Hereticks, or no Members of the Church, or could not be saved, because they erre herein. For confirmation of which consider, 1. By the contrary conclusion we should be excessively <hi>Ʋncharitable,</hi> in condemning to Hell fire, for ought we can find, all, or next all, the Church▪ of Christ for▪ 1300 or 1400 years at least. 2. And we should be very proud in exalting our selves so high above our Brethren, and the Churches of Christ. 3. And it were high presumption and arrogancy to step into Gods seat and pass so bold a <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</hi> 4. And it were great Impiety to make Christ hereby to have no visible Church on earth (nor for ought we can prove, many persons) for so many hundred years: Hereby we should go farre toward the giving up our Cause to the Infidels. For, no Church, no Head of the Church. 5. Hereby we should censure the form of Belief or Profession of all these Churches as insufficient. For the Doctrine of Perseverance now in question, was never (that is proved) in any of their Creeds. Sixthly, Hereby we should foment Divisions in and between the Churches, and make the healing of our Divisions seem desperate. For if we conclude all the Lutherans and Arminians (who yet go further than <hi>Austin</hi> in denying Perseverance) to be uncapable of salvation or of our communion, what room is left for any motions of Peace? 7. And also hereby we should very much encourage the Papists; if we make our first Protestants, <hi>Luther▪
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119090:11"/> Melanchton</hi> and the rest that subscribed the <hi>Augustane</hi> confession, to be Hereticks and persons whose communion was to be avoided. 8. And Lastly, We should be guilty of so notorious schism, as few sober men in the world have been guilty of; I mean in our principles; while we plainly imply that if we had lived in those former Ages that were of a contrary mind to us in this, we would have avoided the communion of them all. I do but name these things briefly, because I suppose that they will find few dissenters. I hope few among us are guilty of such conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions as I gainsay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 7. Hence also it is very clear, that the denyal of the Doctrine of the Perseverance of all the sanctified, doth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily destroy all Christian consolation. It doth indeed tend to the diminishing of it, as to all that have a certainty of their Justification, while it denyeth them the certainty of Perseverance; and while it denyeth to all men a certainty of salvation by ordinary meanes. But it doth not wholly destroy the comforts of the Saints: Nay, it is plain from hence, that a life of much Christian comfort may be had, without assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of salvation. Which I prove, 1. <hi>Adam</hi> might live com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably without assurance of Perseverance or salvation: (thats past dispute: for <hi>Adam</hi> had no such assurance in his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:) therefore a Christian may live comfortably whithout as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of Perseverance or Salvation. There is no dis-parity between <hi>Adams</hi> condition and others in other respects that will weaken the consequence, as long as the case is the same in the point in question.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Being sinless, he had nothing to sadden him, as we have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> True: therefore the uncertainty of Perseverance and of salvation was nothing or not enough to sadden him, or at least, to deprive him of a life of peace. If necessary to our peace, why not to his?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It were unreasonable and uncharitable to think that none of the Ancient Churches that differed from us in this, had Christian peace; that none of the Lutherance Protestants, or Arminians now have peace; that such holy men as <hi>Anstin</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> and multitudes more were deprived of this peace, who have manifested so great confidence and joy both in their lives and Writings. When we read so many of the Ancients
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119090:12"/> and of the Lutherans professing their Peace and joy in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, we cannot pretend that we knew their hearts better than they knew themselves; seeing we never knew the men: nor have we any certain or probable evidence to prove that they wrote falsly of themselves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we could not have joy and Peace in believing, except we receive it from the certainty of our own Perseverance, then it would follow that exceeding few even of them that hold the Doctrine of the Perseverance of all the Justified, have joy and peace in believing. For that Doctrine of Perseverance can give assurance of their own Perseverance to none but those that are certain of their sincerity and Justification. If a man be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether he be sanctified truly himself, he must needs be uncertain whether he shall persevere in that grace which he knoweth not that he hath; yea and in common grace it self. But too sad experience telleth us that there be but few, exceeding few of the godly among us that are certain of their sincerity, Justification, or salvation: I have desired several Ministers that converse much with experienced Christians, and hear them open the state of their souls, to tell me how they find them in this point of assurance? And divers of them of largest ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance tell me that they meet not with one that hath it; but that they all profess some doubting and uncertainty, and none that they ask will say, I am sure. Others tell me that they meet with none that will say they are certain, except some passionate persons, especially women that are melancholy, who are carried on by passionate feelings; and they will sometime say they are certain of this Sanctification, Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Salvation; but it is but in a fit which is quickly gone, and then they are usually in greater doubting and trouble than any others. I confess my own observation is the same or neer it. Amongst many hundreds of Professors, I meet not with one that will say▪ they are certain of their sincerity and salvation, except four sorts; First, Such women or melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people afore-mentioned, who can give no great solid reason for it, and quickly lose it, and are passionate in their conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, Some persons that are fallen into new Opinions and societies, disowning our Profession and our Churches; who presently are rapt up with a seeming certainty that they are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119090:12"/> truly holy and justified; when both their doctrines and lives do cause their soberest acquaintance to fear that they are either proud hypocrites, or deluded Christians, worse than before. Thirdly, Some few very earnest Disputers for Assurance, that will say they are sure of their own salvation, in an eager main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of their Arguments. Fourthly, Some very few judicious holy men, who say they have no strict certainty, nor are free from all doubting; but yet they have so confident a perswasion as may be called a moral certainty, and freeth them from trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some fears of damnation. And these last (though exceeding few) are the highest that ever I met with, whom I have cause to believe, as being judicious credible sober persons. and giving probable evidence in their lives of what they said. I never knew the man that attained any more than such a strong perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, mixed with some doubtings and fears, yet so far overcoming them as to live a peaceable joyfull life.</p>
            <p>Now if Assurance of sincerity and Justification be so rare (and imperfect in the best) then it must needs follow that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of their own Perseverance must be as rare▪ And all these Persons that are uncertain of their Perseverance, can fetch no comfort from that certainty which they have not.</p>
            <p>But yet we cannot conclude that all these persons are void of Christian Peace and Joy: For, first we see by experience that hundreds of these Christians that dare not say they are sure of their Justification or salvation, do yet express much Peace and Joy. Secondly, And the Holy Ghost telleth us that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God consisteth in Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghost; and therefore we may not so farre exclude the most of the Saints out of the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Moreover, the nature of the thing may convince us that a man may live a comfortable life through believing, though he attain not a proper certainty of perseverance or salvation. For a high degree of probability, and a strong perswasion thereupon, may bear down the trouble of most of our doubts and fears. And though it may be objected, that Hell is such a misery, and the loss of Heaven so great a loss, that a man hath no ground of solid grace that is uncertain to escape it, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally considering how little trust is to be put in the slippery will of man: yet (for answer to this) let it be considered. First▪
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119090:13"/> That Heaven is so great a good, that the least true belief and hope of it, may afford abundance of comfort; and Hell is so great an evil, that the least true hope of escaping it, may be very comfortable. Secondly, Yet such uncertainty indeed to a Saint in Heaven would be more troublesome, because it is a condition worse than he is in already: But such hopes, though with uncertainty to the damned in Hell would be unspeakably comfortable; and so should they be to us on earth; because we were before in a state of death, condemned by the Law, and under the curse, and had been actually damned, if death had cut us off. Thirdly, That the goodness of Gods nature, his common mercy to mankind, the fulness and freeness of grace in Christ, the experiences of Gods Love both in common and special mercies, with abundance of comfortable passages in the Scripture, all these may do much to the support and comfort of the soul, against the fear of Apostacy, though there had been no absolute promise of the perseverance of all the Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I argue <hi>a pari:</hi> First, There is no Sonne of the wisest and most constant Father that is certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e shall persevere in the favour of his Parents, and that he shall not fall into their very hatred, and be dis-inherited by them: And yet it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that therefore all Children should uncomfortably vex themselves with fears, lest their Parents should hate them or dis-inherit them: yea, or that no Son may take comfort in the consideration of his Fathers love.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is no Wife that hath the best and most loving Husband, that is certain, he will not hate her and cast her off: And yet when she sees, no probability of it, but much to the contrary, she need not be disquieted by the fears of it; nor forbear the peace and comfort of her condition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is no man of greatest holiness certain that he shall not fall into some odious scandalous sinne; For though there be promises of our perseverance in a state of grace, yet in the judgment of all, there is no promise to the best of us all, that we shall not fall into any such hainous particular sinne. No man is certain but he may be drunk as <hi>Noah</hi> was, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestuous as <hi>Lot</hi> was, or commit adultery and murder as <hi>David</hi> did, or deny Christ as <hi>Peter</hi> did. And if you were sure you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119090:13"/> should fall thus, and wound your conscience, and dishonour the Lord and your holy Profession, would it not even break your hearts? But what? Must all Christians live in doubts and fears of such a thing? Or may not they live in peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort upon the strong probabilities they have of escaping these, though they have no certainty. Yea more; you are not certain but you may for such Capital crimes, be hanged at a Gallows, and made a publique example to the world: And yet I hope we may live comfortably for all that, and need not trouble our selves with such fears save only by necessary caution to prevent the evil. The same grounds therefore which may give you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort against the fears of such scandalous sinnes, may give them comfort concerning their Salvation, who either believe not the Doctrine of the perseverance of all Saints, or are not certain of their own Sanctification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 8. It is fit and needfull that as we maintain the truth of the aforesaid Doctrine of perseverance: so we should withall make known that it is not to be numbred with the most necessary or most evident certain truths, which our salvation, or all our peace, or the Churches Communion doth rest upon: and accordingly that we put it not into our Creed, or Confessions of Faith, which are purposed to express the Fundamentals only, or only those Points which we expect all should sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe to, with whom we will hold communion. As we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it to be a truth: so we must shew (as is done in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Propositions) which rank of truths it belongeth to. For it is a very hurtfull and dangerous thing to the Church, to affirm the less evident controvertible truths to be more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and past doubt, and to affirm those to be of necessity to our Salvation, Communion, or Comfort, which are not so. This is the wrack that hath torn both the Church and the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men.</p>
            <p>Upon this occasion I may fitly give you an account of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of a passage in the Catechism agreed on by the <hi>Worcester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire</hi> Ministers, which I understand some Reverend, godly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, have taken exceptions at.</p>
            <p>In the Seventh Article of that Catechism it is said that [the Holy Ghost doth by the Word enlighten mens understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and soften and open their hearts, and turn them from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119090:14"/> the power of Satan unto God by faith in Christ: that being joyned to Christ the Head and into one Church which is his Body, and freely justified and made the Sonnes of God, they may be a sanctified peculiar people to him, and may overcome the flesh, the world, and the devil, and being zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good works, may serve God in holiness and righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and may live in the special love and communion of the Saints, and in hope of Christs coming and of everlasting life.] Here they are offended at the word [<hi>may:</hi>] because we say not, they <hi>shall</hi> or <hi>will</hi> do these things▪ but only [<hi>that they [may,</hi>] which they say importeth but a <hi>Duty</hi> and a <hi>Possibility,</hi> but not the certainty of the event. To this I answer: 1. Our Question was about the first Participation of Christ and life: and our perseverance is not any part of that, and therefore we were not obliged to determine that controversie in answer to that question. 2. The first [<hi>may</hi>] prefixed to our sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication doth clearly speak of the certainty of the event; for it is impossible the fore▪ expressed work should be done and yet men be unsanctified, 3 Whereas these Brethren object this in their uncharitable suspicion, that we did it to intimate the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy of the sanctified, I must tell them that I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there is not one of the subscribers (to the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st impression, and I think not to the last neither) that doth question the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of perseverance; and that our own meaning is, that the Holy Ghost doth convert us, that we <hi>may</hi> be a holy people and overcome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, that he intendeth this as the event, and useth the former as a meanes to the later; and that God is never frustrate of his intention, and consequently in our sence the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of perseverance is here expressed. 4. But I must adde, (as the principal part of my answer) that we purposely put it in larger termes that all that subscribed might not be necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to understand it as we did: and we purposely avoided the determining of the controversie about perseverance, in the place. We had before drawn up our (prefixed) Confession of faith, which was to be a test of our peoples capacity of Church-Communion in the point of knowledg and soundness in the faith commonly called Orthodoxnes:) and so we were to disown all those that owned not all that was here contained: And when we composed our Catechism, it being in part to the same end, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119090:14"/> partly to be so brief that all might learn it, we agreed to make up the first Eight Articles of the Catechism from the fore-going Confession: so that we were to put nothing in it but the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Salvation or of Communion; or nothing but what we thought we must exact a confession of from all that we would hold Communion with. Now I confess it is far from my Opinion that a man cannot be saved that denyeth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance of all the sanctified, or that we must reject all from our Communion that are of that mind: And I should rather have abhorred than subscribed a confeission, that had contained any such thing, or that had put in the point of perseverance to the ends and on the termes as our confession was subscribed. And this is the true reason of our termes in that Seventh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle; And a hundred other controversall men, may as well find fault with us, for leaving out of our Confession or Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chism the points which they maintain, as these Brethren may find fault with us in this. For we have left out many hundred controversies, whereof very many are as weighty as this. And I despair of pleasing all Disputers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 9. We cannot deny but that the Doctrine of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perseverance of all the sanctified, may Accidentally oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion much more trouble than Consolation, to many doubting souls that are sincere.</p>
            <p>I must confess I have had to do with some my self, that have pleaded this Objection so importunately that a wiser man than I might have found work enough to satisfie them. They say, that [<hi>if they could have any assurance that they are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sanctified, the Doctrine of certain Perseverance of all such would be comfortable to them; but they are brought now into such doubts of it, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y fear they shall never attain to such assurance, being rather induced to conclude themselves certainly unsanctified: For (say they) we never reached so high as some that we have known that have fallen away: We have known divers that have been judicious and affectionate, and constant and lively in duty, and of very upright carefull lives, and so great contemners of the world that they would not have omitted an opportunity for their souls, for worldly gain, yea, they were persecuted and suffered very much for godliness in evil times, and in the sharpest tryals never shrunk, when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119090:15"/> others did, and laid out themselves almost altogether in doing good; their Prayers and Conference were very holy and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and affectionate, and their lives agreeable. so that they were incomparably beyond me in all these Qualifications, and yet some of them now do deny the God-head of Christ and the Holy Ghost; some deny the Scripture, and that there is any Church or Ministry; some are turned Quakers, and some Licentious, if not Infidels; and therefore certainly have now no saving grace. Now before we can ever be sure that we are justified, we must be sure that we go further than any of these did, or any other that ever fell away: Whereas we find our selves far short of many of them. And we are in a manner certain that some of them did not dissemble: both by our observation of their whole course, being intimately acquainted with them, and by the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and openness of some of their hearts, which they manifest even to this day in the way that they are in, being unapt for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simulation.</hi>] I have found it no easie matter to quiet the minds of some that were troubled with this doubt. If we tell them, that these men were gross dissemblers, they will not believe it, nor can I tell them so of all as being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the contrary by my acquaintance with some. If we tell them that at the highest they came short of sincerity, they answer that they have much more reason then, to suspect that they are short of it themselves: and that among an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Professors of Religion, there is not ordinarily two that seem to go further than these men did seem to go: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who can have assurance? If we tell them, that yet God saw the unsoundness of their hearts; they answer, so he may see the unsoundness of mine; For these men did more in self-examination, Prayer, and other meanes to know their hearts than ever I did, and had greater▪ knowledg and helps to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scern them. Some Learned Divines do answer this Objection thus: That it's true, these difficulties and temptations do stand in our waies, but they are no greater then many other temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which we must encounter, and that the Members of Christ have that Spirit, that Teaching, and Anointing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, which will sufficiently relieve them against all such temptations, and do more to comfort them than all the evidences of their uprightness can do, yea, when we do not see
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119090:15"/> our uprightness, nor that we go beyond the persons that have apostatized, in our Qualifications. To this I have known this answer returned; 1. That they know not of any witness of the Spirit to assure us of our justification, but these three; First, The Witness contained in the Scripture, proving the truth of the Promise: Secondly, The Witness of Evidence, contained in the sanctifying Works of the Spirit on the Soul. Thirdly, And the effective Witness of actual illumination and exciting grace, causing us to see our Evidences within, and the truth of the Promise without, and to believe the later, and conclude our justification from both laid together, and to be thankfully and joyfully affected herewith. And many holy Learned Divines and of great experience, profess they have no more, nor know of any more. 2. But if any other immediate revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Testimony of the Spirit without evidence be the thing that must satisfie, comfort, and establish us, those that have such a Testimony or Revelation may be comforted by it, but for our parts we must say that we know not what it is, and never had any such, and know not how to obtain it; and therefore must rather conclude the more confidently that we are unsancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, because we have none of that Witness. And though we have had some sweet delights in Prayer, Meditations and other duties, and some strong perswasions of the Love of God to us, yet we know not whether these were from the Spirit, or whether such delights were not some common▪ work; and those that fell off did seem to us to have more of them, than we could reach.</p>
            <p>For my part, the answer that I usually make to this Objection is this. [Though the falls of others must warn you to take heed, and with a godly jealousie to search your heart more exactly, and to watch over it more diligently, yet God never made the hearts or lives of other men, the Standard for you to try your own by: Nor are you to trouble your Souls by the doubtfull conjectures which you fetch from the former Qualifications of others. God never opened you a window into their hearts: There might be abundance less good and more evil there than ever you suspected in them: <hi>The heart of man is deceitfull above all things: Who</hi> (besides God and himself) <hi>can know it?</hi> And will you run out of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119090:16"/> light into the dark for help to search after your sincerity and Justification? Why you know that God hath told you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressly in his Word, that <hi>he that repenteth and believeth shall be saved,</hi> and that loving him, and loving one another, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeming Christ and eternal life above this world, are the sure markes of Christs Disciples. If you find these in your own souls, what need have you to doubt of them because that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have been deceived? God hath made you more capable of knowing your own hearts than others; and accordingly hath made it your duty to search your own and not theirs: You may know certainly what is in your selves; but you can but uncertainly conjecture at what is in them. And is it fit in your inquiry to try a certain thing by an uncertain? Your own hearts which you know or may know, by other mens which you know not, nor cannot know? This is not the way that God hath appointed you for the tryal of your state: and therefore no wonder if it puzzle and perplex you.]</p>
            <p>Some answer the foresaid Objection by telling them that as in actual sinne (like <hi>Davids</hi> or <hi>Solomons</hi>) the habit of grace was alive under contrary actings: so in the foresaid actual Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, the habit of sound faith may possibly be alive in many that seem to be fallen quite away. Though I do make use of this answer in some cases where there is hope of such habits remaining, yet I am afraid of using it in most of the fore-mentioned cases. I dare not say that a man that long delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and industriously cryeth down the God-head of Christ and the Holy Ghost, and that denyeth the Scripture and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> can be at that time in a state of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion; The comfort is farre fetcht that is given men on such terms; and how we can make it good to them, I know not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 10. Moreover, we cannot deny but that carnal securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not only in hypocrites, but in the godly themselves, may possibly and too frequently take advantage for increase, from the Doctrine of perseverance.</p>
            <p>For the remnants of corruption in us will dispose us to make an ill use of this and many another truth. Hence we are too ready to argue thus; That which is impossible (or certainly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119090:16"/> not future) need not, and ought not, and if known to be such, cannot be the object of rational fear, and care to escape it. But the damnation and the Apostacy of any of the sanctified, is impossible, or not future and known so to be: therefore it need not, and must not be the object of their fear, and care to escape it.</p>
            <p>So on the other side from the necessity of this fear, the Dissenters argue against the certainty of perseverance. That which is known impossible, or not future, cannot be the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of rational fear: But the Apostacy and damnation of them that are now Believers, must be the object of rational fear: therefore it is not impossible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They confess, that yet there may consist with the impossibility of Apostacy, First, An irrational forced fear, which is not a moral act; such as a man would have if he were never so fast on the pinacle of a Steeple, or the top of a steep Rock; Were he most certain to have no hurt, yet it would affrigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him to look down: Secondly, A reverence of Gods Judgments as they shall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon others: Thirdly, A use of means from the sole force of Love, and Faith, to avoid an evil, which yet we have not the least fear of, as knowing it to be impossible. But the fear and care in the Argument, they say cannot consist with this impossibility. For, say they, It is impossible the Act should be without its proper object. But a personall possible evil, called, a danger, is the proper object of that personal fear; for it is a fear of such an evil: therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and so the necessity of this fear they prove from many Texts of Scripture: <hi>Luk 12. 5. Fear him that is able to destroy both soul and body in hell fire.</hi> Heb. 4 1. <hi>Let us therefore fear lest a Promise being left us of entering into rest, any of us should seem to come short of it.</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 27. <hi>I tame or k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep under my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bring it into subjection, lest when I have preached to others I my self should be a castaway.</hi> With many the like.</p>
            <p>To these Objections, there are divers sorts of answers made according to the various principles of the Answerers; some deny the Major, and say that a known impossible evil may be the object of rational fear. To this it is replied, that this is a denying of natural Principles, and the common expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119090:17"/> of mankind; it being agreed on by Philosophers, and felt by all men, that we fear nothing but an evil apprehended as possible. The Answerers say further, that it's true, that if it were impossible in the nature of the thing, we could not fear it: but that which is only impossible by accident or from an extrinsick cause, such as is the Decree, or Will of God, and his Promises may be the object of rational fear: because God hath not simply decreed our perseverance, but hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that by the means of this rational fear we shall persevere, and accordingly commandeth us to fear as the means of our certain perseverance; To this it is further replied, First, That it still denyeth a most undoubted principle, even the definition of fear, and also the common experience of men. For whence ever the impossibility be, extrinsick or intrinsick, reason tells me there is no cause of fear; and all the fear that ariseth about an evil that is known to be impossible is against reason, or without it. An aversion or displacency there may be, but no proper fear of that evil befalling us. And therefore (say they) you feign God to decree contradictions, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. For to decree to give men perseverance by the means of a fear of Apostacy, is to make the evil impossible, and so to be no object of fear, and yet to decree that we shall fear it: And to command a man to fear a known impossible evil, is as if he should command us to love a known evil as such. The earth could not stand an hour if God upheld it not: therefore the ruine or annihilation of it to morrow is in it self possible: But yet as long as God hath told us that it shall continue till the resurrection, and we see that it never failed any one yet, but hath endured through all Ages, reason teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us not to fear the dissolution of this world till the day▪ of Judgment. An impossibility of event from some one cause, doth properly denominate the thing impossible though in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of an hundred other things it were not impossible.</p>
            <p>Some therefore take another course, and say that the Major of the Dissenters Argument is true, but the Minor is false, <hi>viz.</hi> that we ought to fear our not-persevereing, or our damnation. But the Texts are so many and plain that require us to fear coming short of rest, the killing of the soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our not-persevering, that this Answer is not satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119090:17"/> but indeed dangerous, yeelding the Minor to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous and secure.</p>
            <p>Others therefore yeeld the conclusion that our Apostacy and damnation are not impossible, but only <hi>non futura;</hi> (Or which more anon.) But to this it is replied that an evil certainly known to be not future, can no more be the object of rational fear, than that which is impossible. And therefore this hath the same answers as the former.</p>
            <p>For my own part, the answer that satisfieth me, is this: That it's true that a known impossibility or non-futurity of evil doth evacuate rational fear: But then he that will be perfectly freed from that fear, must have a perfect knowledg of the impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility or non-futurity. But Christ and his Apostles knew that those whom they wrote to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d no such perfect knowledg: Nay more, it is not (at least by any ordinary meanes) to be expected in this life, that this knowledg of our sincerity, Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and perseverance should be so perfect as to have no degree of doubting, habitual or actual, at that time or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If no grace be perfect in this life, then the assurance of our sincerity, Justification and Perseverance are not perfect in this life: But the Antecedent is true: therefore so is the consequent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But was not <hi>Pauls</hi> assurance perfect who had been in the third Heavens? Is it possible that he should have any doubt of his salvation? And yet he saith <hi>I tame my body,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>lest when I have preached,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ans.</hi> 1. Those words do not neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily express fear, but the use of a meanes to avoid an evil that without such means would not be avoided. 2. <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was not yet perfect as he professeth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 12. and knew but in part, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 13. 9. and therefore might have use for fear. Though he had special revelations of his salvation, yet his Faith and continued apprehensions and improvement of these, were yet imperfect. 3. If one man by revelation were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly certain, that's nothing to the generality of the Saints. Seeing therefore that we are all imperfect in our certainty of our sincerity and Perseverance, it's meet and requisite that we be called on to a rational working preventing fear, according to the measure of our uncertainty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But these fears then are sinfull, as being the fruits of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119090:18"/> doubts or ignorance, and so you make the Holy Ghost to command men to sin. <hi>Ans.</hi> They are not sinfull, in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, but necessary duties. It's true, that the uncertainty that goes before them is a sinne; but the sears that follow are a duty. Many things are duties to sinfull man in order to his recovery, that would have been no duties if we had no sinne: To believe for pardon, to repent, to pray for pardon, to confess sin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would have been no duties, but on sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of sinne. But when we are once sinners, these are become special duties to help us out of it. And so is it of this fear of falling away and of damnation. But when assurance and love are perfect, and that is, when we are perfect in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, then I shall yeeld that fear of these is needless. In this answer to this great Objection, I rest.</p>
            <p>Therefore, notwithstanding all the Objections that are against it, and the ill use that will be made of it by many, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental troubles that it may cast some Believers into, yet it seems to me, that the Doctrine of perseverance is grounded on the Scriptures, and therefore is to be maintained, not only as extending to all the Elect against the Lutherans and Arminians, but also as extending to all the truly sanctified, against <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> and the Jansenians, and other Dominicans: though we must ranke it but among truths of its own order, and not lay the Churches Peace or Communion upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 11. Though it cannot afford them assurance of salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet may this perswasion of the certain perseverance of all the sanctified, afford much comfort to those that have no certainty of their own sincerity or perseverance.</p>
            <p>If I have no perswasion either of my own sincerity, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severance, or yet of my perseverance as certain if I were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly sincere, then I should have two difficulties in the way of my comfort; which is more than one alone, and therefore must put me further from comfort. But if I were sure that all true Believers shall persevere, if I had withall but a strong hope or probability that I am a true Believer, I should freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the comfort of that probability, without the impediment of further doubts concerning perseverance. When other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise I should be thinking, What if I be justified, yet how can I tell but I may lose it by back-sliding? So that this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119090:18"/> Doctrine of perseverance firmly retained, doth free me from one of the doubts, though not from both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 12. As to the fifth Opinion before-mentioned (which makes either Election or Confirmation causally to inferre perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance) I have said enough on the third and fourth Opinion (which contain this between them) to shew my thoughts of it. Though it be nearer the truth than the rest fore-mentioned, yet I see no ground to believe their supposition, that there is a third sort of truely Justified sanctified Persons▪ that are neither Elected nor Confirmed, and therefore will fall away. As I know of no such▪ degree of habitual grace in this life, which would preserve men from apostacy without Gods continued tutelary, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving grace; so I know of no such thing as true Sanctification and Justification, without that Grace which is radicated in the soul, and so may be called a confirmed state; or without the Antecedent and Concomitant Decree of Gods Election, which layeth a certain ground of perseverance. Sure I am that the ground which received the seed upon a Rock and never gave it depth of earth, did from the beginning differ from the good ground, and so did the thorny grounds: and they seem to me to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that the one sort were never hearty resolved Christians, and the other had never extirpated the love of the world, but had taken up a profession in a subordination to the world, and the flesh which had the dominion. So that if these persons had persevered in that unsound estate, they could not have been saved: For Christ hath assured us that he that loveth any thing, even his own life better than him, and he that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saketh not all for him cannot be his Disciple, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 33. And the house that falleth when the winds arise and the stormes assault it, was never built upon the Rock, but on the sands, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 26. So that I think that which some Papists call a state of Confirmation is the state of every true Christian, and that which they call unconfirmed grace, is but some preparatory grace, that is yet short of a state of Justification; and that which others of them (and most) call a state of Confirmation, which is supposed to be a state of impeccability, is not to be attained in this life; Though I must confess they very much
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119090:19"/> mollifie the matter in their Definitions of sinne and of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, while they make him impeccable or perfect from sinne, that is lyable only to venial sinnes; and make some such venial sinnes, that I know many tender-conscienc't men, that would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth to hold communion with such venial sinners, and loth to keep a servant in their houses that were guilty of such. To make sinne no sinne, and then to say we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and have no sinne, is a near way to perfection; but they that go further about, will sooner come thither.</p>
            <p>This is my present Judgment of their Doctrine of Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace: but yet I am not so obstinate, as to refuse any evidence that may tend to give me better information, if I be mistaken, and therefore shall willingly read what they will say to clear it more. And I marvell to finde so little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and many another of that way, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter, and that those that do touch it, do it so super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially, rather taking the main Point for granted, then offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us any seeming proof of it. <hi>Aquinas 22. q. 24. art.</hi> 8 on the question, Whether Charity may be perfect in this life, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, that though <hi>ex parte diligibilis</hi> it be not (for so only God himself can perfectly love himself) yet <hi>ex parte diligentium</hi> it may, that is, <hi>cum quantum possibile est ipsis, Deum diligunt:</hi> which saith he, <hi>centingit tripliciter: Ʋno modo sic quod totum cor hominis actualiter semper feratur in Deum: Et haec est per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio charitatis patriae, quae non est possibilis in hâc vitâ. Alio modo, ut homo studium suum deputet ad vacandum Deo, &amp; rebus Divinis praetermissis aliys nisi quantum necessitas praesentis vitae requirit &amp; ista est perfectio charitatis quae est possibilis in viâ: non tamen est communis omnibus habentibus charitatens. Terti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> modo ita quod habitualiter aliquis totum cor suum ponat in Deo, ita scilicet quod nihil cogitet vel velit quod Divinae dilectioni sit contratrium. Et haec perfectio est communis omnibus charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem habentibus▪</hi>]</p>
            <p>If the Papists will insist upon this conclusion of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> I shall desire them▪ to consider, 1. That <hi>Thomas</hi> himself doth afterwards affirm that <hi>Perfectio viae non est perfectio simpliciter, ideo semper habet quo crescat.</hi>] Therefore it is but <hi>perfectio se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quid,</hi> and wanting in degree. 2. How will they be ever able to prove that those imperfections of degree are not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119090:19"/> properly sinnes. 3. <hi>Aquinas</hi> in the description of his second sort of perfection▪ doth but huddle up the matter in the dark. For that <hi>studium deputare ad vacandum Deo</hi> considered simply in it self may argue sincerity, but not perfection of degree. Perfection of degree is either that which is the highest that our nature is capable of: and that is only to be had in <hi>Patriâ:</hi> Or the highest that we are obliged to here, and that our natural powers on earth are capable of, if freed from all vitious dispositions; and this may be called <hi>perfectio viae;</hi> but the doubt is whether any man shall attain it: It is such a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as in the way we are capable of, but shall not have. And they that affirm it, must try it by these two things: 1. Hath any man as much Love in Habit and Act as he ought to have, or is obliged to? What man that knowes himself dare say it? Who dare say, I will not be beholden to God, or to the Blood of Christ, for a pardon for my defect of Love to God in act or habit? Yea, were it but for one day, or hour. I must profess for my own part, I am much more sensible of the sinfulness of my soul, for this defect, and of my need of a pardon for it, even in the best day and duty that I pass through (that I can love God no more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously and constantly,) than I am as to any of my external sinnes They must pervert the Law, or pharisaically boast of what they have not, before they can say that they do love God with all the heart, and mind and strength▪ in the sense which it requireth as to the degree, and to uninterrupted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of their love.</p>
            <p>2. And they must measure it also by their Natural Powers: If they love him in intention and constancy of exercise, as much as our Natural Powers are able▪ if they were perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sanctified, or habituated thereto, and perfectly freed from all sinfull dispositions, then indeed they have that which may be called here perfection of degree: But this no man hath. If the Natural Powers can love God no more then they do (<hi>in sensu composito</hi>) because they are clogged by vicious dispositions, or are not elevated and rightly disposed by due habits, this is its moral impotency, and is farre from proving it innocent or perfect, that it is the very sinne and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it self. If this be perfection, perhaps the damned might
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119090:20"/> be called perfect. But if any man dare say that his soul is perfectly habituated, and freed from evil dispositions, and doth exercise Divine Love, and all other graces, alwaies, <hi>ad Ʋltimum posse,</hi> to the highest capacity that the right disposed Natural-Powers-<hi>in viâ,</hi> can reach, I am past doubt that that man is a stranger to his own heart, and an unhumbled Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risee. Their making concupiscence in the habit or act to be no sinne (added to their fore-mentioned Doctrine, that venial sinnes are but sinnes Analogically, and not properly) is but a sorry way to lead men to perfection. We confess that the ordinate habitual or actual sensitive Appetite is no sinne: But withall we must say, that in sinfull man this Appetite is corrupted, and become inordinate and rebellious, and the phantasie infected with sinfull sensual habits, and no man here perfectly freed from these (besides the remnants of sinfull dispositions in the superiour powers of the soul.) And we dare not say that these are not sinnes; and consequently, that man is perfect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 13. As to the sixth Opinion (of the Amissibility of a state of Infant Justification, or rather the cessation of it) which is a point of great difficulty, and a controversie (though not much agitated) among the most Learned of the Reformed Divines, I shall for divers Reasons at this time purposely forbeare the delivering of my Opinion in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 14. As to the controversie contained in the Seventh and Eighth Opinions, I think it is but verball, and is to be dispatch't by several distinctions of possibility and impossibility. To omit divers others that might conduce to the decision, these few at present may suffice. 1. We must distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an Impossibility in <hi>re,</hi> and <hi>extra rem;</hi> or <hi>a causis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsecis,</hi> or <hi>a causis extrinsecis</hi> or else accidental. It is possible that true grace be lost, if you speak of a possibility <hi>a causis intrinsecis &amp; de natura rei;</hi> that is, the habit and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject together. But it is impossible that it should be totally and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119090:20"/> finally lost, if you also respect the extrinsick causes: And that both <hi>per impossibilitatem consequentiae;</hi> because it is not possible that these Propositions should be both at once true. [God willeth absolutely or fore-knoweth that <hi>Peter</hi> will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>severe] and [<hi>Peter</hi> will not persevere.] (And yet this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is reconcileable with the first [It is impossible <hi>in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura rei</hi> for <hi>Peter</hi> to fall away.] And also 2. <hi>Per impossibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem causae;</hi> First, Because God hath not only decreed the perseverance of the sanctified, but also the Holy Ghost hath undertaken it as his special charge. Secondly, And the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness of God, (as farre as I can yet understand it) is by his Promise engaged for the perseverance of all the truly Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and sanctified Believers; and, I am sure, for all the Elect that are such: which made the Lord Jesus himself judge it a fit speech to say, [<hi>They should deceive if it were possible the very Elect,</hi> Mat. 24. 24.] intimating that it is not possible so to deceive them; and that is, because they are Elect; even an extrinsick accidental impossibility. It's a dry evasion of them that expound the Elect, of <hi>praevisi perseverantes;</hi> as if Christ had said [It is not possible to deceive them that God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowes will not be deceived.] For there is some present cause here plainly intimated of their perseverance or future non-deception; and it is not a meer logical impossibility of consequence that is spoken of. And if this cause was within them, then it must be the nature or degree of their grace: If without them, it must be the Election and preservation of God, which indeed was the cause.</p>
            <p>For my part, I subscribe to <hi>Aquinas</hi> his explication of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in 22. <hi>q. 24. art. 11. Ʋtrum charitas semel habita possit amitti?</hi> as it lieth in these words in conclusion which I think worth the reciting though somewhat large [<hi>Quanquam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae charitas, ubi Deus per essentiam videtur amitti nullatenus possit; charitas tamen viae, in cujus statu Dei essentia non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur amitti peccando potest.</hi> (But marke the Explication) <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spo. dicendum quod per charitatem spiritus sanctus in nobis habitat. Tripliciter ergo possumus considerare charitatem. Ʋno modo ex parte spiritus sancti moventis animum ad diligendum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: &amp; ex hac parte charitas Impeccabilitatem habet</hi> (I would say it is <hi>inextinguibilis</hi> or <hi>inextirpabilis) ex virtute spiritus sancti, qui infallibiliter operatur quodcunque voluerit:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119090:21"/> Ʋnde impossible est haec duo simul esse vera, quod spiritus sanctus velit aliquem movere ad actum charitatis, et quòd ipse charitatem amittat peccando. Nam donum perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae computatur inter beneficia Dei quibus certissime libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur quicunque liberantur ut</hi> Aug. <hi>Alio modo potest considerari charitas secundum propriam rationem: &amp; sic charitas non potest aliquid, nisi id quod pertinet ad charitatis rationem: Ʋnde charitas nullo modo potest peccare, sicut calor non potest infrigidare, &amp; sicut injusticia non potest b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um facere, ut</hi> August. <hi>Tertio modo potest considerari charitas ex parte subjecti quod est vertibile secundum arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trij libertatem. Potest autem attendi comparatio charitatis ad hoc subjectum, &amp; secundum universalem rationem qua compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur forma ad materiam; &amp; secundum specialem rationem, qua comparatur habitus ad potentiam. Est autem de ratione formae, quod sit in subjecto amissibiliter, quando non replet totam potentialitatem materiae—sic ergo charitas Patriae quia replet totam potentialitatem rationalis mentis (in quantum scilicet omnis actualis motus ejus fertur in Deum) inamissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter habetur. Charitas autem viae non sic replet potentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem sui subjecti, qui non semper actu fertur in Deum. Ʋnde quando actu in Deum non fertur, potest aliquid occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere per quod charitas amittatur. Habitui verò proprium est, ut inclinet Potentiam ad agendum: quod convenit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitui in quantum facit id videri bonum quod ei convenit, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum autem quod ei repugnat. Si ut enim gustus dijudicat</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Aquin.</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. <hi>Gentil.</hi> lib. 3. qu. 155. fol. 125.</note>
               <hi>sapores secundum suam dispositionem: ita mens hominis dijudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat de aliquo faciendo secundum suam habitualem dispositio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem: Ʋnde Philos. dicit, Quod qualis unusquisque est, talis finis videtur ei. Ibi ergo charitas inamissibiliter habetur, ubi id quod convenit charitati non potest videri nisi bonum, sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet in Patriâ, ubi Deus videtur per essentiam, quae est ipsa essentia bonitatis: &amp; ideo charitas patriae amitti non potest. Charitas autem viae, in cujus statu non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idetur ipsa Dei esten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, quae est essentia bonitatis, potest amitti</hi>] (that is, in respect of the subject alone considered) I take this for a plain and sound explication of the point: if the rest were added, <hi>viz.</hi> in whom the Holy Ghost doth thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve Grace.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119090:21"/>
            <p>And here I cannot see but <hi>Aquinas</hi> is against <hi>Alvarez</hi> conceit of a confirming grace in this life, which is a participation <hi>charita. 'tis Patriae:</hi> For <hi>Aquinas</hi> confineth <hi>charitatem Patriae ad patriam,</hi> and excludeth it <hi>a viatore:</hi> and he confineth it to the Vision of God <hi>per essentiam,</hi> which both he and the truth do exclude from earth. And <hi>De veritate Mater.</hi> 18. it is his first Qu. and he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth that it is an Error in them that think that <hi>Adam</hi> in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency did see God <hi>per essentiam,</hi> though imperfectly, and in a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le sort <hi>inter statum beatorum &amp; peccatorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See also <hi>Capreolus Defens. li. 2. Dist. 23. qu.</hi> 1. of this.</p>
            <p>Yet of the main point <hi>Aquinas</hi> speaks as <hi>Alvarez</hi> before cited. And most fully <hi>lib de verit. Mater. 24 qu. 9. fol.</hi> 137, 138. where he concludeth that <hi>in viâ</hi> no man can be perfect and confirmed in good <hi>simpliciter, ita viz quod in se sufficiens, suae firmitatis princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium habeat quod omnino peccare non possit:</hi> but only <hi>per hoc quod datur eis aliquod munus gratiae per quod inclinantur in bonum, quod non possunt de facili a bono deflecti: non tamen per hoc ita retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huntur a malo quod omnino peccare non possint, nisi divinâ providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ custodiente.</hi>] And <hi>ad</hi> 4<seg rend="sup">m</seg> he thus qualifieth his perfection [<hi>Quod ex ratione illa potest haberi, quod non est aliquis in statu viae omnino confirmatus, sicut nec omnino perfectus.</hi> (And <hi>ad</hi> 5<seg rend="sup">m</seg> adds that <hi>posse peccare non facit ad meritum, sed ad meriti manifestatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem;</hi> which the Jesuites may consider of.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 15. The ninth Opinion being the Libertines, is so gross against nature, and express Scripture, and the very holy nature, and the experience of the Saints, that I think it not necessary here to say any more of it, than to disclaim it, and open the truth in these few Assertions. 1. No mans assurance of his perseverance is perfect in this life: 2. Therefore in that measure as his assurance is imperfect, and he is lyable to the least doubts, in that measure it is his duty to fear: The fear may be a duty, when the doubt that doth occasion it is a sin. 3. A very great cautelousness according to the weight of our work, would be necessary, if our assurance of perseverance were perfect. 4. God hath not only decreed and promised that we shall persevere, but also that we shall by the means of this holy cautelousness, and solicitude and fear, persevere: <hi>Jer. 32. 40. I will put my fear in their hearts that they shall not depart
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119090:22"/> from me.</hi> 5. The dominion of any one sin is inconsistent with sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace and justification. 6. Therefore he that is under the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of any sin, may be sure that he is unjustified, but he cannot be assured that he hath that holiness or justification which he hath not, or that he shall persevere in it, before he have it. 7. He that hath not more hatred than love to any sin, and that had not rather be rid of it even in the use of Gods means, than keep it, in regard of the habituated state of his will, is under the dominion of sin, and in a state of damnation. 8. He that is thus resolved and affected against a gross sin, or any known sin that is under the power of his will, is not like to live in, or give up himself to it: Nay he cannot commit it without renewed resolutions against it, and a restless importunity of soul to be delivered, which will prevail. 9 It is therefore a great suspicion, if not a certain thing, that the man that can live in such a sin, and quiet his mind in it on this account, that once he had grace, and therefore shall persevere, is yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out true saving grace. 10. Sin doth as naturally breed troubles and fears as the setting of the sun causeth darkness, or as a gross substance in the sunshine causeth a shadow. And this from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing, and by the will of God. 11. A lapsed Christian must be recovered, and fear is one of the means of his recovery. 12. Therefore the Libertine Doctrines, of not fearing, mourning, praying, confessing, in order to pardon, are pernicious Doctrines: as I have more fully manifested in other Writings on that Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 16. As to the tenth Opinion, which affirmeth that no measure of our first st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck of grace can be lost, which was infused in our regeneration; I distinguish between two sorts of converts: In some God may put at the first but the smallest degree of saving grace; and perhaps that may be Gods most ordinary way: And then no doubt, that cannot be diminished, but the sincerity or life it self must be lost: For the diminishing of the smallest sparke would be the extinguishing of it. But for ought I know, in others God may give a greater measure of grace in their first conversion, than to most he doth after long use of means. I think he did so to <hi>Paul.</hi> Now in this case, though it is most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that God never will suffer that grace to be brought to a smaller measure then at first it was infused, yet I know no certainty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119090:22"/> by Promise or any other proof that he will never permit such a diminution. Let them that affirm it, bring us their evidence, and we shall try and judge of it as we find it.</p>
            <p>A godly Divine M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>John Barlow</hi> in his Discourse of Spiritual stedfastness gives this Reason. [<hi>As we were patients at the first reception, so are we no agents in its destruction. Lose we may what addition, by our co-operation with it we have gained: but not the least dram of that which without our co-working, was at ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> effectual call infused.</hi>] To which I answer. 1. It's but barely said, that we are no agents in it's destruction; and not proved. I deny the consequence: A man may be active in destroying grace, that was but passive in receiving it. 2. We may merit the diminution, and so may be active. 3. It is not yet proved, but that we are as truly passive in receiving each superadded degree, as the first; or that every degree is not infused as the first was: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough it be true that there are higher preparatory dispositions in the soul for further degrees than were for the first. 4. This whole Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is confuted by the instance of <hi>Adam:</hi> For he was as passive as we in receiving his first grace, and yet lost it, and was too active as to the losing it: therefore the reason is insufficient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 17. The Eleventh Opinion, (that no degree of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit can be diminished, either which was first infused or after added) is less probable than the former; And M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Barl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w</hi> in the foregoing page doth give four Reasons against it. And yet not only some few of ours, but most of the School-men, are against the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the habit; but very differently, for though <hi>Aquinas</hi> simply say that [<hi>Quanquam charitas secundum se ac directe, nullatenus diminui possit, dispositivè tamen &amp; indirecte per venia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia peccata &amp; cessando ab operibus virtutum diminution<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit</hi>] Yet <hi>Gr. Ariminensis,</hi> and abundance other School-men adde that <hi>ex natura sua potest diminui, &amp; si non potest respectu ordinationis divinae:</hi> And their denyal of the diminution of it, is from their false Opinions about venial and mortal sin. <note n="*" place="margin">And the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctrine of the Thomists against the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y by addi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of further degrees, doth lead them to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk it cannot be diminished. Against which see <hi>Rada.</hi> contr. 18. and other Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ists.</note> For they feign a thing called venial sinne, which is not against charity, nor, properly sinne, and then they give that as a reason why it cannot directly (that is, <hi>neque effective neque meritorie</hi> as <hi>Aquin.</hi>) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minish charity. And then for mortal sin, they say it doth totally
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119090:23"/> evacuate and corrupt Charity, both <hi>effective &amp; meritoriè: Aquin 22. qu. 24. art. 10. concl.</hi> But it will be long before they will be able to teach their Scholars to know which are mortal and which venial sinnes, according to their own descriptions, (so truly doth <hi>Gerson</hi> and with him others, complain of the difficulty of discerning them:) and longer before they will prove any sins to be venial in their sense: and as long will it be before they will well prove that every sin which they call mortal doth <hi>charitatem totaliter corrumpere</hi> as they affirm; and that <hi>Peter, David, Noah,</hi> &amp;c. were utterly void of Charity when they sinned, and were afterwards new-born a second or third time. I think I need not stand upon their Reasons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prop.</hi> 18. As for the Twelfth Opinion which is the Libertine of that strein that are next the Familists, I have said so much a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst it in other Writings, and so many others have said more, and it is so gross as before was said of the Ninth which draws near it, that I shall suppose I may be here excused from med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with it any further, than to bid the weak and unskilfull to beware of it, as being a ready way to carnal security, impiey, liceniousness and perdition.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 8. l. 12. for [<hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>destination</hi>] r. [<hi>predetermination</hi>] p. 10. l. 21. for [<hi>violaris</hi>] r. [<hi>viatoris</hi>] p. 21. l. 37. for [<hi>grace</hi>] r. [<hi>peace</hi>] p 37. l. 6. for [<hi>impossible</hi>] r. [<hi>possible.</hi>]</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>